A Guide to the Harry Lyons Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
- Newsletters, Bulletins and Journals 1951-1975
  - Journals and Publications. 1931-1987 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Journal of the Canadian Dental Association 1960 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. 26 No. 5
    - Proofs, the Dental Trade Journal. 1964 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. 47 No. 5
    - Profiles, The Virginia Cultural Laureate Society 1988 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Endowment Opportunities 1988
      VCU Endowment Proposition.
- Convention Programs and Flyers. 1940-1966
  This folder contains convention programs and folders from many dental conventions. Associations included are the American Dental Association, American Dental Trade Association, American College of Dentists, American Association of Dental Schools, American Academy of Periodontology, and several state dental associations.
  - National Association conventions. (Box-folder 7.1)
  - State and Local conventions. (Box-folder 7.2)
- Photographic Collection. 1922-1976
  This series focuses on Lyons many awards and professional gatherings. Also it includes some personal photographs.
  - Early dental school photographs 1922 (Box-folder 8.1)
    Lyons with sister Tillie Lyons and Constance Haller. These were two of the first women admitted into the MCV Dental School.
  - Groundbreaking of the Wood Memorial Building 1951 (Box-folder 8.2)
    (Audio on cassette)
  - 12th International Dental Congress 1957 (Box-folder 8.3)
    Rome, Italy (See Folder 3.29)
  - 55th Hawaiian Territory Dental Society meeting 1957 (Box-folder 8.4)
    Honolulu, Hawaii
  - U.S. Navy Dental School 1958 (Box-folder 8.5)
    Bethesda, MD (See Folder 4.7)
  - Senate Commission of Consultants on Medical Research 1959-1960 (Box-folder 8.6)
    (See Folder 3.37)
  - Hebrew University Hadassah School of Dentistry 1960 (Box-folder 8.7)
    (See Folder 3.36)
  - University of Manitoba, Dentistry faculty. 1960 (Box-folder 8.8)
    (See Folder 3.77)
  - American Association of Dental Schools 1961 (Box-folder 8.9)
    (See Folder 3.5)
  - Dental Class Reunion 1963 (Box-folder 8.10)
    (Classes 1918, 1923)
  - American Dental Association 1947-1963 (Box-folder 8.11)
    Photographs of multiple events and functions.
  - American College of Dentists 1963 (Box-folder 8.12)
    (See Folder 3.8)
  - New York University College of Dentistry 1965 (Box-folder 8.13)
    (See Folder 3.51, 3.54)
  - National Conference of Christian and Jews 1966 (Box-folder 8.14)
  - VCU/MCV miscellaneous photographs (Box-folder 8.15)
    (See Folder 3.84)
  - Dedication of the Harry Lyons Building 1970 (Box-folder 8.16)
    (See Folder 3.83, 3.84, Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - Groundbreaking of the Harry Lyons Building 1967 (Box-folder 8.17)
    (Groundbreaking audio on reel-to-reel; naming ceremony on reel-to-reel, cassette)
  - Baylor College of Dentistry 1973 (Box-folder 8.17)
    (See Folder 3.23, 9.3)
  - Virginia Dental Association Bicentennial 1976 (Box-folder 8.19)
    (See Folder 3.67, 4.40. Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - Friends of Tel Aviv University 1976 (Box-folder 8.20)
    (See Folder 3.64, 3.65)
  - VCU/MCV Outstanding Alumni Award 1987 (Box-folder 8.21)
    (See Folder 3.96)
  - Undated photographs (Box-folder 8.22)
    These photographs are of Lyons' birth certificate, and early dental advertisement.
  - Miscellaneous Photographs 1950-1960 (Box-folder 8.23)
    This folder includes photographs of Lyon's receiving awards and speaking.
  - Professional Portraits (Box-folder 8.24)
    Photographs for use in publications and other official uses.
- Artifact and Award Collection
  This series contains several artifacts and bound volumes
  - Miscellaneous artifacts 1828, 1868, 1892 (Box-folder 9.1)
    This folder contains a special tax receipt for a dentist office from the Internal Revenue Service, 1868. A ticket for the 1892 Democratic Convention, and a dental school text dated 1828.
  - Yearbook, Dental Columbian 1955 (Box-folder 9.2)
    Columbia University
  - Yearbook, The Baylor Burr 1973 (Box-folder 9.3)
    Baylor Univerisity
  - Awards and Certificates (Box-folder 9.4)
    (A-N)
  - Awards and Certificates (Box-folder 9.5)
    (M-P)
  - Awards and Certificates (Box-folder 9.6)
    (Q-Z)
  - Awards and Certificates (Box-folder 9.7)
    Oversized. Held in oversized storage.
- Scrapbooks 1953-1957
  This series contains two scrapbooks each chronicling Lyons' professional career.
  - American Dental Association scrapbook. 1956-1957 (Box-folder 10.1)
    This scrapbook highlights Lyons work with the ADA. A folder with clippings found in back of book, 1950-1967. This scrapbook contains mostly newspaper clippings and official newsletters.
  - Sara Wice Lyons scrapbook. 1953-1958 (Box-folder 10.2)
    This scrapbook was compiled by Lyon's wife and covers his professional activities. This scrapbook contains much more in the way of photographs, and memorabilia.
- Audio Recordings 1954-1984 (Box-folder 11)
  This series contains audio recordings of Lyons on multiple formats.
  - Audio Recordings
    The following audio tapes are part of their respective series but are held within the Audio Collection.
    - "President's Address, A.A.P." (Box-folder 3.3)
      cassette
    - "Testimony to Harry Lyons" (Box-folder 3.100)
      7 in. reel-to-reel
    - "Achievement" (Box-folder 4.1)
      7 in. reel-to-reel.
    - "The Crystal Ball" (Box-folder 4.7)
    - "Dentistry and the Future" (Box-folder 4.12)
      5 in. reel-to-reel.
    - "Opportunities in Dentistry" (Box-folder 4.28)
    - "Two Centuries of Dentistry in Virginia" (Box-folder 4.40)
  - "Interview with Alden Aaroe of WRVA radio. On the occasion of the opening of the Wood Memorial Building." 1954 (Box-folder 11)
  - "Wood Memorial Building dedication" Feb. 01, 1954 (Box-folder 11)
  - Interview with John Wingate of the Home News from NY. 1956 (Box-folder 11)
    5 in. reel-to-reel
  - "Groundbreaking of Dental Building Two (Lyons Building)" Nov. 08, 1967 (Box-folder 11)
  - "Dedication of Dental Building Two (Lyons Building)" Jan. 26, 1970 (Box-folder 11)
  - "Naming ceremony of Lyons Building" Jan. 26, 1971 (Box-folder 11)
    5 in. reel-to-reel, cassette
  - Oral History Interview, Temple Beth Ahabah Feb. 22, 1972 (Box-folder 11)
  - "Opening remarks, VCU/MCV endowment fund workshop" Jan. 31, 1982 (Box-folder 11)
- Video Recordings 1959, 1985, 1987 (Box-folder 12)
  This series contains video recordings of Lyons on multiple formats.
  - "Patterns of a Profession" 1959 (Box-folder 12)
    American Dental Association centennial, 16mm color sound film. 2x 11 in. reels. Stored with Film Accessions.
  - "Dean's Fund testimonial" 1985 (Box-folder 12)
    VHS videotape
  - "Virginia Dental Association meeting" 1987 (Box-folder 12)